Welcome to the 2026 release wave two
launch edition of Business Central. This
session is about uh reporting,
specifically layout management and
report inbox APIs. This is the video one
of three
um and we're going to talk about layout
management in general and report inbox
APIs. So, um
let's see what that is. So, back in the
fall in the spring release in wave one
of 2026, we added the ability for an
layout administrator on the report
layouts page to set kind of a a status
of the layouts so that they could
control which layouts are ready to
consume and which are still kind of in
the making.
And we that was only for user-defined
uploaded layouts, but we are now
extending this to app-supplied layouts
including the layouts that we ship with
Business Central out of the box.
So, here on the report layout page, you
now have a new menu called layout status
where you can set a layout
um kind of a life cycle starting from a
draft, um pending approval, approved,
and retired. And
there's nothing changed on the report
layouts page. You can still run any
layout you want from this page.
So, in this case, I can run the
financial report landscape even though
it is um
set as retired. Note that in this
example, I actually set one of the
Microsoft-supplied
layout to retired.
So, as an administrator, I can still run
everything from that page, but whenever
a user touches the report layouts
control in the request page,
they can only see approved layouts
there. So, this is a way for you as an
administrator to control exactly which
layouts are approved for use usage out
there with the users. And you can still
experiment as much as you want with
making the the next ones available. And
if there are some of the layouts that we
ship in the base app from Business
Central that you say, "These are not for
us." you can make sure that users cannot
use those layouts.
Also, for any layout that is shipped
from an app, whether it's a patent and
extension and ISV app from AppSource or
Microsoft, we have this ability for a
developer to put a summary or
description for a layout. And you can
actually override that
now and kind of put a comment like,
"We don't like this layout." or "This is
not for us." or whatever. And you can
override that developer comment
so it shows up in the report layout page
and
and actually also the version of that
for users.
The second feature we are giving you as
administrators is an ability to to
interact or have agents or automation
interact with the report inbox.
So,
report inbox is used for anything where
things are scheduled,
reports that are scheduled, reports in
finance or reporting that are scheduled
or report packs. All of that lands in
the users' report inbox. And
therefore, they the users can have
agents
do more things with that.
With Power Platform,
with MTP server, with Microsoft Copilot
Studio, or any other tool that speaks
APIs.
The new APIs are easiest to find them is
to go to the new API overview page that
we are also shipping here in version 29.
Um, search for report inbox and now
you have both the
API names and also the URLs if you want
to try them out.
That's basically it for now for this
video. Just a final thing, if you want
to learn more about reporting as such,
uh, if you use the landing page
aka.ms/bcdeveloper,
scroll down to the report section and
everything about reporting and layouts,
uh, you can learn that there. And
everything related to integrations and
the new API, you find that on the
landing page for integrations, which is
aka.ms/bcintegration.
And there, uh,
everything related to each type of API
is documented there.
That's it for this video in the launch
edition. I hope you will watch many of
the other, especially the two others on
reporting,
and, uh, have a great day. Bye.